ELM HAVEN, IL

Dan Simmons

Introduction

(the original, unpublished story Introduction)

Summer of Night and the following short story, “Elm Haven, IL” both take place in a fictionalized version of my real hometown: Brimfield, Illinois.

Summer of Night has sold well in the United States and has been translated into almost a dozen languages. Readers in Europe, Japan, and elsewhere seem to have the same fascination with “Elm Haven, Illinois” circa 1960 as American readers do: a time of relative innocence for kids, long summer days, and an almost forgotten freedom when kids could jump on their bikes in the morning and return after dark without anyone worrying.

Summer of Night was more about the “secrets and silences of childhood” than it was about monsters, but not completely, as you will see . . .

Night has always been, for me, the only gentle time. Night is the Forgiver and the Acceptor. Night is the time to stir abroad and to walk the empty streets of our small and dying town. I sometimes dream of Night being a sister to me in my suffering; I hear her consoling whispers in the summer shuffle of leaves above the shadowed walks and imagine her lullaby in the slide of snow on snow during the long winter dark.

But most often, Night seems a parent to me. She is the mother who takes the place of the one who abandoned me three days after my birth; he is the father who replaces the one who died or disappeared the week before that birth. Night is the coddling parent who rocks me with its breezes, breathes on me with its warm summer fragrances, and who conceals me from all the cruel and curious eyes.

I only go out at night. The people in our little town—this dying little town—know the scrape and shuffle of my dragging walk. They know the tap of my cane along the dark pitches of tilted sidewalks between the streetlights. They know the rasp of my breathing and the rustle of my beekeeper’s veil. They know my stench.

They do not fear me. No one locks their doors at my approach. I am part of their town and a piece of their night Sometimes there will appear a pale face at a window as I lurch by in the not-quite-shrouded dimness of a late summer twilight, but the face is always as familiar to me as my veiled countenance is to them, and more often than not I will receive a wave and a smile.

I wave back with my good hand, my uncloaked hand. But I do not smile beneath my veil.

And then, one mid-August night in this summer just past, everything changes. Everything.

Old Settlers Weekend is, I think, as old as our town of Elm Haven, Illinois. I have seen photographs that go back to just after the Civil War. Old Settlers has always fallen on this same weekend in August—in the heart of summer but close enough to its end that generations of Elm Haven’s children have taken the weekend carnival as the last knell of freedom before the descent of school, hard weekends of work in the harvest-rich fields, and winter, and the end of everything that childhood is about.

So I was not surprised in the dark hours of a late- Thursday, early-Friday night to see the colored lights and to hear the shouts of roustabouts from just beyond our sheltering ring of city trees. The Old Settlers carnival was being set up—as it always was—in the fields north of town and east of First Avenue, out in the meadows beyond the city baseball diamond and overgrown football field, between the water tower and the town.

I dragged and scraped my dead leg and misshapen foot down Depot Street to the abandoned Somerset place, through the overgrown yard reeking of wisteria gone wild, and then over a sagging fence—tugging my cloak and veil away from brambles and wire—and finally out into the field where the carnival was being erected. The bright lights had been extinguished now, the generators were silent, and only starlight and the gleam from a waning moon illuminated the pale canvas of tents being raised and the paler sheen of skin on the bare backs of roustabouts laboring to raise them. The carny rides already had been set into place, the dark shapes of the Ferris wheel and Mad Mouse looking like metal gallows designed by madmen. The tents were rising quickly. I stood there in the predawn chill and listened to the hollow thud of great mallets pounding stakes deep into the chest of our Illinois earth.

This was not the Old Settlers I had known for almost three decades. Usually, Old Settlers Weekend is celebrated with fish fries and fireworks and baseball tournaments and water fights between our local volunteer firemen. The three huge tents always belonged to the JayCees, the American Legion, and the WCTU. Two of the big tents sold beer and food, the third only food and soft drinks.

The carnival itself was a smaller, secondary thing, usually consisting of a three-ride midway and half a dozen smaller tents where our citizens could lose their money at the ring toss or shooting galleries or Guess-Your-Weight or other pleasant silliness.

But not this year.

This year the tents and rides and booths and sideshow trucks filled the meadow and lopped over onto the dusty football field. The main tent was larger than the three-pole American Legion tent that had always dominated Old Settlers. The rides were bigger, more dangerous looking. The game booths filled a hundred yards of grassy avenue like the midway of a real circus.

This was a real circus. I could hear large animals breathing and smell their reek over my own stench. Somewhere in the huddle of dark trucks at the far end of the field, an elephant trumpeted softly. A second later a lion or tiger or some other big cat coughed.

I felt goose bumps rise along the skin on my normal arm. I moved forward from shadow to shadow until I was in among the long trucks. I ran my hand—my cloaked and deformed hand—over the baroque letters of the painted sign along the trailer’s side: Peabody-Ozymandias Traveling Circus and Oddity Emporium.

The words seemed charged with electricity. I felt what little hair I had rising along my deformed brow and the fingers on my good hand twitched as if from palsy.

There was movement in the shadows. Gasping more loudly than usual, almost unable to hold my head erect in the dizziness that suddenly assailed me, I crouched low, pulled my veil tighter inside the neck of my cloak, and scrabbled for the darkness of the overhanging trees. But other shapes moved faster, dodging between cab and trailer, between tent and sideshow booth. Men’s deep voices set up a hue and cry.

Panting, wheezing, my lungs full of liquid and my bad leg dragging, I lurched around a dark comer of a truck and began scraping toward the dark row of trees thirty yards south.

Two men were on me in a second.

“Jesus,” said the first. “What’s that stink?”

“What the fuck . . .” said the second, and ripped away my beekeeper’s hat and veil. I winced at the fresh air.

Both men stepped back. One raised a bare forearm to his mouth and nose. “Hey, Nolan!” shouted the first man.

A third man appeared. Even in the dim moonlight I could see the muscles on his thick upper body, the blood- red slash of bandana tied around his head.

“Look at this, willya?” said the first roustabout. “I never seen one of the freaks tryin’ to sneak into the show before. You believe this shit?” He leaned lower and tugged loose my cloak. The second roustabout stepped farther back and made a gagging sound.

“He looks like a melted candle made outta lizard skin or something,” said the first roustabout. “Makes of Tripper Rawley look like Tom Cruise, don’t he?”

“Shut up,” said the man named Nolan. He gestured toward the second roustabout. “Take him to Prather.”

I closed my eyes and did not resist as they lifted and carried me back into the maze of canvas and steel.

Despite the late hour, the man they called Prather was awake and at the table in his trailer, looking toward the door as if expecting me. He waved the two roustabouts away and then gestured me toward a chair. I did not sit. Regular chairs are difficult for me.

“My name is Ozymandias Prather,” said the big man in a voice that sounded as if it were being boosted by microphone and amplifier. The light was dim in the trailer, but even so I could see a certain slackness in the large man’s face that did not seem to match the energy in his voice. The muscles of that face twitched into a smile. “My friends call me Oz,” he said.

I blinked. The roustabouts had tossed my beekeeper’s hat onto the floor of the trailer and I longed to put it on, but bending and lifting it would be too awkward in front of Mr. Prather. I pulled my cloak as tight as I could and backed away from the lamplight.

“No,” said Mr. Prather. It was a command. I stood still in the light. “What is your name?” he asked softly.

I did not answer. Few could understand my speech—Old Sook could, but she was dead; Father O’Rourke could, but he was not here.

“What is your name, brother?” Mr. Prather said. The “brother” startled me. The big man looked to be in his early or midforties; I was thirty-one. But the word had come easily enough to him and it still echoed in my consciousness. Brother.

“Benjamin Willis Ashley-Montague,” I muttered, knowing that he would not catch a clear syllable of it.

“Well, Benjamin Willis Ashley-Montague,” said Ozymandias Prather with a smile, “we’ll have to come up with a shorter version of that or we’ll both be worn-out just saying each other’s names. What do you say I’ll be Oz and you’ll be Benjamin?”

I could only blink stupidly. He had understood me. “Don’t move, Benjamin,” said Mr. Prather as he rose quickly, pulling me slightly toward him. “No, no, it’s all right. I just want to see you in the light.”

I winced as he came so close, and watched his eyes and nostrils, waiting for the usual narrowing and flaring as he saw my deformed flesh, smelled my fungous stench. His slack face showed no reaction. His hands were firm but impersonal as they moved over my bulbous skull, the terrible proboscis-shelf that was my cheek and upper lip, the wattles of tumorous reptile flesh beneath my neck and above my chest.

Finally, he stepped back. “Do you know the cause of your condition, Benjamin?”

I nodded, a ponderous dip of misshapen skull. “Elephant Man Disease,” I whispered. I knew the words sounded like nothing more than a random rattling of stones in a broken cup.

“And what is Elephant Man Disease, Benjamin?” Mr. Prather’s soft smile had not wavered.

I took a breath, trying not to expel it in his direction. I knew that my breath stank of inner decay. “Multiple neurofibromatosis, von Recklinghausen’s disease,” I said, knowing that even Old Sook could not have understood me now. “A genetic disorder. It affects about one person out of every three thousand . . .” I paused, but Mr. Prather seemed to be waiting for more. I could not believe that he could make out what I was saying.

“In most cases,” I continued, hearing the rasp and slide of my own tongue in the malformed cave that was my oral cavity, “. . . in most cases, it just results in discoloration . . . spots on the body . . . some small tumors . . . and a ten percent chance of retardation. In more advanced cases . . .”

Mr. Prather tilted his head, a tutor ready to prompt a faltering student.

I did not falter. “In more advanced cases . . . like mine . . . there are freely hanging pedunculated tumors distributed irregularly over the skin, other tumors made up of fibrous and connective tissue cells and malformed nerve fibers along the subcutaneous nerves. Also . . .” I took another breath. “Also, I have the Elephant Man syndrome of scoliosis . . . severe curvature of the spine . . . and a malformed skeletal structure.” I waved the paddle of my bad arm at him, tugging up the cloak a second so that he could see the finlike thing that grew there where a hand should be. I did not offer to take off my slippers so that he could see the malformed feet, or lower my cloak so that he could see the thirty-pound, hanging, wrinkled masses where my buttocks and thighs should be.

Ozymandias Prather nodded, went around behind his desk, and sat down. “No,” he said.

I blinked three times. “No?” Old Sook had taken me to the best specialist in Illinois when I was a baby. I had read volumes on the disease. Multiple neurofibromatosis. Elephant Man Disease. There was no doubt.

“No,” repeated Prather. His voice was firm. “You have the same disease as Joseph Merrick, Benjamin . . .”

Joseph, I thought. He knows.

“. . . but it isn’t NF. The doctor who diagnosed you was wrong. Dr. Treves . . . Mr. Merrick’s surgeon . . . was wrong.”

I shook my head in confusion and had to brace myself against a chair to keep from Ming. “But—”

“The disease you and Joseph Merrick share is called Proteus syndrome,” he said. “It wasn’t described until 1979. Drs. M. Michael Cohen, Jr., and Patricia Hayden were the first to isolate it Proteus syndrome explains the grossly abnormal bone growth you and Merrick obviously share . . . the malformed, wrinkled bumps on your feet and elsewhere . . . the bony bumps on your head and cheek.” He paused, perhaps seeing me writhe in what he might have thought was embarrassment but was nothing more complicated than self-disgust. “Proteus syndrome,” he said again.

I tried to speak, but no words formed, only rattling, echoing noises in my slippery proboscis of a jaw: a malodorous wind in a damp cave.

Ozymandias Prather knew what I was so desperately trying to say. “No,” he replied softly, sadness audible in that booming, oddly amplified voice, “there is no cure, Benjamin. Proteus syndrome is even less well understood than neurofibromatosis.”

He did a strange thing then: Mr. Prather bent retrieved my beekeeper’s hat, set it on my misshapen skull, tucked in the little elastic strap Old Sook had attached so that my malformed chin held the hat in place, and arranged my veil so that my face must have been less than a shadow to him.

I turned to leave.

“No, wait just a moment, Benjamin. I have something to tell you.”

I paused by the door while he spoke. The explanation took only a moment or two, but I felt as if I were riveted there for days, weeks, while new worlds opened at my feet.

Ozymandias Prather explained about his father’s dismantling of a wonderful Device . . . I could hear the capital D in his voice . . . and about the Piece that he was sure was still around Elm Haven somewhere. He explained how the completed and activated Device would realize a wonderful change in the world, how it would somehow confer both justice and a new appreciation to those of us who had been unfairly treated as freaks. Mr. Prather explained how he lived for that day of ultimate justice.

“You are how old, Benjamin?” he asked at the end of his story.

“Thirty-one,” I said, my voice choked with emotion now as much as with phlegm. No one had ever asked me my age before.

“And your birthday?”

I felt my eyes water beneath their bony ridges. “August eighteenth, nineteen-sixty.”

Ozymandias Prather nodded to himself. “That would be about right, Benjamin. One of the Pieces could well have been left in this area just about that time.”

I did not understand. In my confusion, I turned to go. Beyond the open door, the sky was beginning to pale.

“Benjamin,” he called as I made my way clumsily down the trailer steps, across the dew-dampened grass, “if you find the Piece I spoke of, I will grant you your wish.”

“What wish?” I said. My garbled voice made one of the big cats growl beyond the wall of trailers.

“Your wish to join the freak show,” said Mr. Prather as he closed the door.

I stood there for a long moment, not blinking, barely breathing. How did he know?

Finally it was daylight that drove me back into the darkness of the trees and then home.

Despite what you have heard, or read, or seen in the movies or on stage, the Elephant Man’s name was Joseph Merrick, not John Merrick. The Elephant Man’s friend and savior, Sir Frederick Treves, had inexplicably (and incorrectly) referred to Merrick as John in an essay written years later, and John he has remained.

Joseph. Joseph Merrick.

Socrates once said, “A name is an instrument of teaching and of distinguishing natures.”

Dr. Treves, in the same essay where he repeatedly referred to Joseph as John, wrote of his disfigured friend’s nature: “As a specimen of humanity, Merrick was ignoble and repulsive; but the spirit of Merrick, if it could be seen in the form of the living, would assume the figure of an upstanding and heroic man, smooth browed and clean of limb, and with eyes that flashed undaunted courage.”

I have the quote hanging over my bed in the tunnels behind the mansion, the ink on heavy parchment still as legible as the day I copied it when I was seven. Old Sook was a good tutor. And I was a willing student.

Joseph Merrick.

My name is Benjamin Willis Ashley-Montague. A name is an instrument of teaching and of distinguishing natures.

All that long August Friday, I lay in the cool tunnels beneath the greenhouse behind the ruined mansion and thought of where the Piece might be hidden. In the early afternoon, four or five of the town kids visited me—the Cahill boy, the Catton girl, the Daysinger twins, and, I think, the retarded Sperling youngster who rarely spoke. The children were not afraid of me; their parents had grown up with me and the children themselves had seen me all of their lives. Still, it required somewhat of a dare for them to come down into the chilly tunnelway under the greenhouse to talk to me in my home.

Today their excitement could not be contained. They wanted to tell me about the wonderful circus and freak show that had come to town. Only Tommy Cahill realized that the prattle about freaks might embarrass me, and he elbowed little Judy Catton every time she babbled on about the “Oddity Emporium,” but Judy and the others were so enthralled and oblivious that they would elbow Tommy back and continue with their breathless descriptions.

“You gotta see it, Bennie,” Judy finished, her grin showing her missing front tooth. “It’s the neatest thing that’s ever happened to stupid old Elm Haven. Honest!”

Then the children were gone, rushing home for more fudgesicles and then back out to the fairgrounds to watch the JayCees finish putting up their tent in the stultifying heat.

I lay in the suddenly quiet dimness and thought about where the Piece might be. Mr. Prather had said that it might have been hidden in or around the town about the time I was born.

From what I could tell from Old Sook’s senile prattle before she died, from old photographs and newspapers I had seen, and from my own earliest memories, our town was nothing like what it was in 1960, when I was born. Like me, Elm Haven had been dying and decaying almost since the day it had been conceived.

I had read in the County Historical Gazette that Elm Haven had had more than 4,000 people in 1875, the year a huge old county school had been built in town to hold the droves of children of the new residents the community had anticipated. The droves did not appear. The school was built, abandoned by sections, and had burned down the summer I was born. There were fewer than two thousand people still living in Elm Haven that year of 1960, but photos of the old town then still reflect a certain vitality and hopefulness.

It was the three decades between then and now that seemed to have delivered the coup de grace.

In the year I was born, the bastard child of a Peoria millionaire and a poor white-trash Elm Haven girl, Highway 151A still was the main thoroughfare between Galesburg and Peoria, and the traffic helped keep two restaurants, a tavern, the A&P, a dry goods store, and half a dozen other downtown establishments running. In the late sixties, Interstate 74 bypassed the town by six miles and traffic on 151A all but disappeared. Now the only people going through Elm Haven are probably driving to Elm Haven . . . and that is very few people indeed.

By this summer, the town’s population has dropped below a thousand and most of them are old. The children of my generation have mostly fled to cities for work and for the ease of commute and for the civilized amenities of cable television, decent restaurants, and movie theaters, as well as for the anonymity which seems so necessary for sanity these days. Even when Elm Haven had restaurants and the occasional Free Show movie, it never offered anonymity. It never will.

By this summer of 1991, the great elm trees which had given our town its name more than a century earlier are dead—carried away by the Dutch elm blights of the sixties and seventies—and the previously leaf-shaded streets lie naked to the sun. The once-fine old homes along Broad Street have been sold by the heirs of the families who had owned them since the Civil War, have been bought and “renovated” by Peoria or Chicago yuppies seeking a quieter life, and most have been sold again by those same yuppies fleeing back to the city. The “renovations” mostly consist of shag carpet, sybaritic open “master bathrooms,” and rewiring projects that were never completed. Some of the big old homes still stand empty, their garish paint jobs and add-on redwood decks looking like cosmetic finery hastily applied to a corpse. Other homes have been sold to locals at bargain prices and are rotting away without maintenance or care. Only a few, like Doc Staffney’s old home and the Grossaint place, still attempt to keep up standards.

By this summer, Elm Haven’s Main Street, Old Highway 151A, looks like a smile that has lost most of its front teeth. The old A&P has long been closed—locals use the Stop’N’Shop QuickStore out at the 1-74 exit eight miles away—and, after a short reincarnation as a secondhand thrift shop, the old market was bulldozed to leave room for future expansion along Main Street. The dry goods store also was leveled, along with Myers Hardware next door. But no future expansion has occurred. So now, at least along the north side of Main Street, there are a few remaining buildings with cheap facades—Farmers’ Commercial Bank, the empty Catton Mercantile building, Mr. Denofrio’s barbershop—separated by great gaps of gravel and weeds.

Nothing has been bulldozed along the south side of the two blocks of Main, but it might have been a mercy if they had done some razing. The old Texaco on the east edge of town has been closed since 1964 and only the most desperate tourist, low on gas, pulls into the ancient pumps there. I have watched, late at night, as tourists in the glare of their own headlights stand peering at the prices frozen beneath the glass of those dust-covered pumps—twenty-seven cents a gallon, read the tin numerals—and I have smiled beneath my veil as the tourists curse and bang at the pumps as if threats will bring back those days, those prices.

West of Ernie’s Texaco, the Parkside Cafe has been closed since ’74—I remember going to the back door for free Cokes until I was well into puberty—and the John Deere dealership down the block closed in 1976. (Sarah Dean Sperling, the untalented daughter of the town’s mayor that year, was paid two hundred dollars to do a huge Bicentennial mural along the side of Farmers’ Commercial and that awkward excrescence has survived all of the entropy that has claimed so many of the good things about Elm Haven. It flakes there now on the east side of the bank, the stick-figure pioneers and coonskin-capped frontiersman looking faded but indelibly idiotic.) Bandstand Park next to the abandoned cafe is treeless now, the once-proud gazebo bandstand reduced to a slab of pea green concrete, the benches no longer painted or repaired. Only the pigeons, a few senile old pensioners and I patronize Bandstand Park. I sit there frequently on summer nights and try to imagine the days when my grandfather (and then my lather) showed outdoor movies there—the Free Show—between the early days of World War II and the year I was born. It must have been a pleasant thing, lying there on blankets on the new-mown grass, in the shade of the elms, watching the Free Show while evening settled in and the stars came out between the leaves.

The park is empty now, the grass overgrown by weeds or worn away by erosion, but the War Memorial Monument near the sidewalk is still cared for and updated. Three names were added to the bronze plaque for service in Vietnam—Father O’Rourke’s is one, I was amazed to note some years ago—and I hear that one will be added for the Persian Gulf War. Young Greggie Whittaker, an idiot during his high school days who almost killed himself in his daddy’s Subaru, did manage to kill himself while driving an army truck over there in Saudi Arabia three weeks before the air war began. The older residents in town flew American flags all during that conflict, but only the Whittakers felt it was worth flying theirs at half- staff.

Carl’s Tavern was the last place to die, closing down in the early eighties. Local patrons now drink out at the Black Tree near the Catholic cemetery, or drink at home. There’s been a lot of drinking at home through the recessions of the seventies and eighties and, now, the nineties. The trickle-down theory never trickled all the way down to Elm Haven.

So where can Mr. Prather’s Piece be? I ask myself as evening fells. I climb up to the greenhouse and set my knobbed brow against the grimy glass. Bats flit and dodge above the brambles and between branches over the ruins of the mansion. Where could it be?

Every town has its unsettling places. Some are outright evil. Others are just . . . unsettling. These places seem to gather power in Elm Haven in the late summer, when perspiration lies between your skin and clothes from morning until night, when the cornfields have grown until they block out the light like walls of green darkness, and when the sky seems haze-hidden and brooding.

Where?

As the older residents and few remaining children of Elm Haven move off toward the lights and circus noises of Old Settlers, I hobble out into the all-but-abandoned town, seeking out the Piece. Seeking my salvation.

Dr. Frederick Treves revealed in his essay that Joseph Merrick used to have two recurring fantasies. The first was that of being a lover—in the Victorian sense—a gentleman who charms the ladies. “He was amorous,” wrote Treves. “He would like to have been a lover, to have walked with the beloved object in the languorous shades of some beautiful garden and to have poured into her ear all of the glowing utterances that he had rehearsed in his heart.” Merrick himself fell in love with almost every lady he met after his admission to the safe haven of the London Hospital. It was for his actress-friend, Mrs. Madge Kendal, that Joseph Merrick constructed the elaborate model of St. Philip’s Church as a gift. That model still stands in the hospital, framed near the glass case holding Merrick’s twisted skeleton.

Joseph Merrick’s other dream was to visit a land in which everyone was blind.

I understand both dreams. To be loved and admired. To be seen for oneself. And I understand that for him—as for me—it could only happen in the kingdom of the blind.

Even as I enter the warm embrace of Night, seeking Mr. Prather’s missing Piece as my admission to his family of freaks, I dream of loving and being loved. I dream of the happy time after the Device is finished.

That night I searched the bad places.

While the calliope tunes from the merry-go-round and the shouts from the last game of the evening’s baseball tournament and the screams from the Mad Mouse drifted east and south across the town, I scrabbled through the charred ruins of my father’s family’s mansion.

The timbers and broad oak floorboards had charred and fallen into the basements and subbasements, and all of this wreck and rubble was overgrown by brambles. But Old Sook had shown me the secret way in from the greenhouse basement near where my own tunnels began. I squeezed and puffed and panted and tugged my cloak free as I wormed my way between old foundation stones.

I found nothing but spiders and rats there in the cellar of the house my great-grandfather had burned down in his fit of madness just after World War I. As a haunted house, the ruins of the Ashley-Montague Estate held only promise or disappointment, no reality.

Pulling on my hat and veil, I scraped my way down the sidewalk along Broad Street. The branches of the Chinese elms and young oaks that had grown up since the death of the great elms there came nowhere near spanning the wide arc of street, but they gave me deep shadow through which to move.

The Duggan house was empty, boarded-up, either truly haunted or merely run-down enough that not even our yuppie invasion of the early eighties had threatened it with purchase or renovation. I let myself in between planks of loose plywood on the side door.

The place smelled of mildew and rot and rat droppings. Small things scurried in the walls where I was and larger things scrabbled claws along the hallways of the second floor. I was not afraid. Night was my sister and mother.

Mrs. Duggan, the last occupant of the house, had been no local witch or monster, only a pedantic old sixth-grade teacher who had died of cancer months before I was born. But local legends among the kids then and now insisted that the old teacher had been seen in town after she died, that the old woman’s rotting corpse had been spied shuffling through the corridors of the abandoned school in the months before the structure burned down.

It was nonsense, of course. Kid stuff to frighten future generations of kids. But it had done its job; even now, thirty years after the poor lady’s demise, Elm Haven parents could finally call in their playing children from the last bit of play in summer’s long twilight by shouting—“You’d better hurry, before Mrs. D’s ghost comes out!” The kids would come galloping for the safety of electric lights.

There were no working electric lights in the ruins of Mrs. D’s once-proud home. But I had brought a flashlight in my cloak.

Every town deserves a haunted house like this one; Mrs. Duggan’s furniture had never been removed. Childless, without heirs willing to travel to the wilds of central Illinois, the teacher could not have foreseen that her house would remain much as she had left it when she left for her final hospital stay. In recent years, prowlers and vandals and thrill seekers had carried away souvenirs until only the heavier pieces of furniture remained, shrouded in dust and cobwebs and darkness.

I spent almost two hours in Mrs. D’s haunted house. I searched the downstairs rooms where footprints in the dust showed me where the adventurous had gone before me; I searched the velvet-shrouded upstairs rooms where there were fewer footprints and cobwebs had reclaimed the doorways. Incredibly, the old woman’s hairbrush and toilet set were still laid out on an age-yellowed and dust- grayed doily atop her bureau. A begrimed mirror made me lower the veil from my hat, even though I could barely see in the dark. The canopied bed had been soaked through from the leaking ceiling and had collapsed into a rotted mass on the floor. Small white things burrowed into the mattress as I shined the flashlight beam across it.

Nothing of interest upstairs. No Piece.

Mr. Prather had said that he did not know the shape or size of the Piece, but that it would be small—almost certainly smaller than six inches in length or circumference. He had said that it would probably be made of metal, but might also be made of ceramic or something like it. He said that it might be buried or hidden among junk or held as a prize possession in someone’s safe, but that I would know it when I saw it.

How? I had asked.

You will know it, Benjamin, he had said.

There was nothing in Mrs. D’s haunted house that struck me as anything but a relic of some sad teacher’s moldering legacy of rot and local superstition. I even searched the basement, where legend had it that Mrs. Duggan’s dentist father had left his chair and tools.

They were there. The dental picks and cumbersome drills were rusted so badly that they looked like some barnacle-encrusted instruments of torture brought up from a Spanish galleon. The dentist chair had rat holes chewed in the dusty fabric. Small things scraped and scurried behind dripping brick walls as I wheezed my way up the stairs.

There was no Piece.

North and west of town, out along the gravel roadbed where the Monon Railroad tracks had been tom up a quarter of a century earlier, there was an old tallow plant cum grain-elevator complex where even the most adventurous of high school students would not go on a dare.

I took my flashlight with its fading batteries and hobbled out there. A child could have run there from Broad Street in five minutes. It took me almost an hour to make the trip.

The door of the central building was sagging free of its massive hinges. There were no cobwebs here, no dust- covered portraits with eyes that followed the intruder—none of the Disneyland haunted-house ambience of Mrs. D’s home. But the emptiness was somehow worse.

There were large iron hooks that hung down over a steel trough running across the center of the first-floor space. The hooks had been added after the grain elevator had gone out of business in the recession following World War I. It had been a tallow plant for only a few years, but the hooks were stained with something deeper than rust, and the steel trough had been scoured black. A chill wind blew in through broken panes.

It was the perfect place for Mr. Prather’s father to hide a Piece. The place would already have been abandoned thirty years ago—even forty or fifty—and, in the back room, there was a heap of scrap iron of every possible shape, size, and function. I spent hours there, my flashlight beam growing weaker and weaker until I was sorting shapes of iron in almost total darkness, until finally I gave up, laboriously rose from my good knee, and felt around for my cane.

The Piece was not there. I felt no recognition. The cold iron was only cold iron. The only resonance I received from that place was the disgust and loathing when I ventured too near the hooks and trough. Something had been butchered and bled there.

Something not meant to be butchered.

Sighing, my breath rattling in my proboscis of a mouth, I began scraping and pulling my way back into town. It was after two a.m., the lights of Old Settlers had been dimmed for almost an hour, but I would wait in the line of trees along the water tower ditch north of the playing fields until it was safe to see Mr. Prather.

Again, he seems to be waiting for me.

I begin to explain my failure, but he holds up one hand. “No explanations are necessary, Benjamin. I know that you will find it.”

I have nothing to say to that. Embarrassed to stay, unwilling to leave, I touch my veil the way a man will stroke his beard when at a loss for words.

“Come here, please, Benjamin,” he says and leads me to the dark end of his trailer.

There is a machine there: something Gothic and clumsy out of the twenties, all vacuum tubes and heavily shielded wires and glass plates the size of upended tables. I begin to back away.

“No, no,” Mr. Prather says softly, taking me by the arm and moving me between the glass plates. “It is only my father’s X-ray machine. Very old, but I’ve modified it to be very safe.”

I make a series of sounds that no living person could have understood.

“Why take an X-ray?” he repeats. Even while he speaks, he is positioning the equipment, throwing a switch that brings a deep hum to the room, and sliding in heavy photographic plates. “My father used it . . . I still use it . . . to make sure that the . . . ah . . . performers in my Emporium are in good health.” He smiles at me. “It is amazing how few doctors, even specialists, have any idea of the health needs of the physically exceptional.”

He smiles again, steps far back into the dark, and says, “Take a deep breath, let it out, and do not move until I tell you to.”

I inhale and then rattle an exhalation. The hum grows louder. The ancient apparatus clicks and groans.

“Fine, fine,” says Mr. Prather. He removes plates, hands them to someone waiting just outside the door. “Why don’t we have some tea while we wait for them to be processed, shall we, Benjamin?”

I do not actually drink the tea. The noises would be too embarrassing. But I do pretend—lifting the delicate china cup to my proboscis, the little finger of my good hand lifted as I do so. Time passes.

There is a knock and Mr. Prather excuses himself. He carries three large X-ray transparencies to a small light table between his closet and the rear of the trailer. I am standing only three feet behind him, but I cannot see the pictures. I feel it would not be polite to ask to do so. In truth, I do not want to see them; I have seen the photographs of Joseph Merrick’s skeleton from the London Hospital.

Mr. Prather clicks off the light. His face seems more slack than ever as he turns. “I’m sorry, Benjamin. Actually, I had been hoping that the problem with your spine might be cured. Treatment of scoliosis has come a long way since Mr. Merrick’s day. But I’m afraid it is too severe.” He looks down a second and when his face bobs back up, the smile is attached again. “But the good news is that you seem very healthy. All of the internal organs that I can make out are well-formed. Do you feel well?”

“I have never had a sick day,” I say in all honesty.

“Good, good,” says Mr. Prather and he moves me to the door. His hand on my twisted shoulder feels firm, friendly. “You know that we will be leaving before sunrise on Sunday?”

I nod. My face does not allow the usual expression of emotion—both smiles and frowns are impossible for me—but I feel the tears forming in both eyes. I tug down my veil to conceal them.

“I know you will bring me the Piece by then, Benjamin. Have no concern. I have none. You will come by after the last show tomorrow night, yes?”

I nod again. I almost stumble on the small step of his trailer, but he touches me again, steadies me. I realize that he is patting me on the back.

Moving away through the dark maze of tents and trailers, I no longer try to stop the tears.

Old Sook brought me to the specialist in Peoria when I was six years old. I remember the tests, the stares, the whispered comments as more and more specialists were brought in to look at me. I remember the equipment, how cold and large and intimidating it all was. I remember how I hated to be naked in the bright lights and how chill the air was.

When it came time to report to us, I remember the consternation on the doctor’s face as he held his report in his hand and frowned at the old woman and the bizarre child across the desk from him. Finally he had set the report down, given me a candy to suck on, and taken Old Sook into an inner room to speak simply to her. I remember her cries and shouts from the other room before we left the hospital.

But most of all, I remember the taste of the peppermint candy as I turned the report around and began reading it. I was only six, but Old Sook had taught me to read almost two years earlier. I knew that I would not have time to read it all or to work out the hard words, so I lifted the carbons out of the file and slipped them in my shirt.

Now, almost twenty-five years later, the carbons are smudged, the paper yellowed, but I can still make out the words:

The subject is a slight male Caucasian, six years two months old. Intelligence appears normal or above-normal (Wexler) and there is no sign of emotional disability other than an extreme shyness which may be the result of physical abnormalities and a home environment in which the child is being raised by a seventy-two-year-old “Auntie.” . . .

Radiology: The skull is the seat of extensive asymmetrical bony outgrowths affecting the frontal, left, parietal, left temporal, and left half of the occipital and sphenoidal bones. Osseous growth is not accurately bordered by the sagittal plane, but extends to the right frontal and occipital regions. Bony masses involve the entire frontal region except for a small area above and behind the right angular process. These masses are extremely irregular and may be divided roughly into three portions by two deep longitudinal sulci. The left sulcus is practically continuous with the supraorbital notch . . .

The bones of the subject’s face are deeply affected. The lower end of the left nasal bone is prolonged into a rough prominence which encroaches on the anterior nares. The left malar bone has a prominent boss just external to the infraorbital foramen. The alveolar process of the maxilla projects strongly outward at its lower extension while a second, rougher mass runs nearly horizontally inward.

Spine: The subject exhibits extreme scoliotic curvature to the right in the dorsal region, the vertebrae being also rotated. The transverse processes in the mid and upper dorsal regions are oversize and rough on the right side. The atlas has a large boss, nearly two-and-a-half centimeters in thickness, on the right side of the anterior arch. The left lamina of the fourth cervical vertebra is also thick and extruded.

Epidermis: The subject’s skin is subject to papilloma ranging from a mere roughing of the integument to great masses of hanging papillomata. Such masses cover the back and gluteal region. Subcutaneous tissue is massed in regions where the integument is raised prominently above the surrounding epidermal layers. This tissue is loose and can be raised from the deeper parts in great folds.

In the left pectoral region, at the posterior aspect of the left axilla, on the inner sections of each thigh, and over the buttocks, the affected epidermal layer forms heavy, pendulous flaps which may be manipulated with only slight discomfort to the subject.

The subject’s left ulna is large and rough. The greater sigmoid cavity is distorted. The malformation of the inner lip of the trochlea throws the forearm out from the arm at an angle of 150 degrees. The bones of the left carpus are large and friable. The metacarpals and phalanges of the index, left, and little Angers are distorted, cartilage-webbed, soft in texture, and incapable of articulation. The bone of the left thumb presents normal characters but is imbedded in a fibroid mass.

Supplementary observation: The diffuse tabulated tumors which cover the subject’s back, chest, and buttocks, as well as the undifferentiated papillomas, reflect direct involvement with innumerable sebaceous and sweat glands, as well as with other secretions from internal vessels and cavities. The resulting bacterial decomposition of secretions within these papillomatous masses causes the subject to emit a powerful and unpleasant odor.

Diagnosis: Multiple Neurofibromatosis with scoliotic rotation and generalized Hyperstosis with Pachydermia.

Prognosis: Anecdotal evidence and examination suggests a rapid spread of the neurofibromatosis symptoms within the past year. While surgery can eliminate some of the more obvious papillomata and relieve some of the scoliotic effects, irreversible involvement of bony masses on the skull, left arm, pelvis, and spine, as well as the rapid spread of tumors throughout fibrous and nervous tissues, suggest continued spread of the disorder through puberty and beyond.

I lie in my nest of pillows in the tunnel and remember the first time I read those pages, and I remember the look on Old Sook’s face as we rode home in her friend Gabriel’s 1948 Buick, and I think about how Joseph Merrick chose to die.

He laid his head back on his pillow and went to sleep.

Like me, Joseph Merrick had to sleep sitting up in a nest of pillows, his ponderous head propped upon his knees. Otherwise, the weight of his own skull would break his neck.

He laid his head back on his pillow and went to sleep.

I have thought of this every night and morning of my life.

But this morning, as Elm Haven slowly comes to life after its long night at Old Settlers revelry, this morning I listen to the few traffic sounds and I am not tempted. Not this morning.

I will find the Piece.

On Saturday evening, just after dusk, I begin the long trip out to Calvary Cemetery.

I make the long walk up the alley between Broad Street and Fifth, cut through the fields north of Catton Road, come down around the water tower past the lights and sounds of Old Settlers, and strike out through the edge of the cornfields bordering Jubilee College Road. It is a little over a mile and a half to the cemetery. I figure it will take me four hours to make the walk.

The car pulls over before I can blend away into the tall corn and a voice says, “Ben? Is that you? Come on out, Ben.”

It is a voice I can not ignore. I move out of the darkness of the field.

“What the hell are you doing out here, Ben?” asks Father O’Rourke. “Where are you headed?”

I tell him.

The priest stares at me a moment and then opens the passenger door of his Honda Civic. “Well, the pope mobile’s headed that same direction, kiddo. Hop in.” I believe that Father O’Rourke only calls the parish car the popemobile when it is just the two of us talking. It is, I think, a private joke that I never understand and he never explains.

We roar the remaining mile and a quarter in less than two minutes. There are twenty or more trucks and cars visible as we pass by the Black Tree Tavern, tucked in like piglets to a sow’s teats, Father O’Rourke says, and then we zoom down the narrow paved road through the woods, and then up to the cemetery.

It is not quite full dark when Father O’Rourke opens the black iron gate and waits for me to enter. He sees my hesitation. “I’m just going to pray out here for a few minutes, Ben. You do what you have to. I’ll wait for you in the car until you’re finished.”

Still hesitating, I look at the priest . . . my friend. He is in his early forties but even with a beard he would look younger if it were not for the thin spiderweb of scars that creep up the left side of his face. His hair is cut short and is thinning on top; he has a sunburn. When I finally drag myself through the gate, I notice his own limp as he follows.

Father O’Rourke is an Elm Haven native, one of the few of his generation who stayed. Returned, rather, for the priest had first left as a young man of nineteen to go to war. It was in Vietnam that Father O’Rourke had lost much of his left leg. I had not failed to notice the symmetries of our afflictions.

Rumor in town has it that the priest had been a tunnel rat—one of those unfortunate volunteers who crawled into Vietcong tunnel networks. Rumor in town says that he had been very good at his job of tunnel rat, right up to the time he tried to squeeze past a decomposing NVA trooper’s body in a narrow passage only to find that the body had been booby-trapped. Rumor in town whispers that Father O’Rourke spent fourteen months in the veterans’ hospital, that he joined the Franciscans as soon as he was released, and that he had been an outspoken defender of the rights of the poor in Central America right up to the time two years ago when the Church had forced him to leave because they were fearful for his life even if he wasn’t Rumor in town has it that Father O’Rourke could have taken a teaching position in any Catholic university in the nation, but that he chose to return to Elm Haven as a simple parish priest even though his parents had died and his sisters and friends had moved away.

One never immediately notices Father O’Rourke’s slight limp or the plastic prosthesis of a leg. With Father O’Rourke, one notices the laughter and the enjoyment of life that seem to gleam behind his gray eyes. One notices his kind voice and strange sense of humor. One notices his courage.

I watch him limp away down the first row of headstones, and then I turn and limp away myself, toward the back of the cemetery.

The utility shed there is in little better shape than my great-grandfather’s mansion, but there had been no basement, so whatever tore the north and east walls apart and collapsed the roof had left the bones of the old structure intact. The shed is not on consecrated ground. There is enough left that the groundskeepers still kept their shovels and lawn mowers stored there.

There is no padlock on the door but I do not open it. I set my good hand against the warped wood. The door seems to vibrate slightly.

Children hate this place. I have heard about “Van Syke’s Shed” from children of my generation and the others that followed. Kids who would happily spend the night in an open grave in Calvary Cemetery will make wide arcs around the shed. No one knows why. There is no legend surrounding the place, no campfire tales of ghosts or ghoulies.

But children hate this place.

The vibration against the door seems to fade. I feel a vague nausea, a dizziness that moves from my feet to a place behind my eyes.

But it has nothing to do with the Piece. I know that now.

On the ride back to town, Father O’Rourke speaks softly. “You’re looking for something, Ben.” It is not really a question.

He glances at me. “Does it have something to do with the circus, the new mud show that the town council brought in?”

I do not know what a mud show is, but I know what he means. I look away, absurdly fearful that he can read my eyes through the darkness and the veil. The night wind through my open window is redolent with the smells of moist earth and growing corn.

“There’s something wrong with that show, Ben,” says Rather O’Rourke, his eyes moving from the road to me. We are only going fifteen or twenty miles per hour and there is no other traffic along the county road. “Do you feel that?” he asks.

I do not answer.

Before we reach the area where the lights of Old Settlers fill the intersection of Jubilee College Road and First Avenue, Father O’Rourke stops the car. He reaches over and grips my good hand. “Ben, I know you’re lonely, but whatever the hell’s going on, don’t let loneliness guide your actions.”

I can hear the midway sounds coming down the dark road.

Father O’Rourke sighs. “Are we friends, Ben?”

I have to answer that. “Yes.”

He squeezes my hand. “Then, as a friend, do you promise that you will come to me before you do anything . . . before you have any dealings with those people at the freak show?”

I hesitate only a second. “Yes,” I say. At this moment, I do not think that I am lying.

Father O’Rourke keeps his gaze on me a second, then squeezes my hand a final time. “Okay. Good enough. Where do you want me to drop you?”

“The schoolyard,” I say.

If the shed behind Calvary Cemetery was avoided by kids, the schoolyard in the center of town was shunned a hundred times more earnestly. No one knew why it was hated by children. There was no school there and had not been one there for three decades, but the land had never been used for anything else. Playground equipment stood rusty and unused. Town kids would walk blocks out of their way to play baseball at the city diamond out by the water tower rather than venture onto the old playing fields of the schoolyard.

I could have started my quest for the Piece here, but I also hated the schoolyard. There was no reason for my fear, but the fear was real enough. This was the only place

I had ever encountered where the Night was neither sister nor parent, but something dark and malevolent.

Father O’Rourke watched me for several minutes as I stood by the edge of the schoolyard. I stood staring back through my veil. Then the priest held up his hand in what I first thought would be a fist or beckoning gesture; instead, he made the sign of the cross, a benediction. I did not move until he drove away, the taillights of the popemobile disappearing down Depot Street

The foundation of the old school lay in the center of this square of blackness in the heart of Elm Haven. The old stones and bricks were almost flush with the ground. The deep basement had long ago been filled in, the charred timbers carried away to the landfill out beyond the dump. There was nothing to mark the site of the old school except the foundation stones, looking like the low headstones I had just seen out in the cemetery.

Teenagers in Elm Haven dared each other to step across that line of stones. None did.

I did. Closing my eyes, cursing my own cowardice, I stepped across the foundation stones and dragged my dead leg out into the center of the great, dark square. Cinders scrunched under my good foot and left a wake behind my bad one.

I stopped in the center.

I hated this place. I hated the feeling that flowed over me here like black water in a cave. I hated the darkness deeper than darkness that seemed to rise from the foundation stones behind me and seal this place from the rest of Elm Haven . . . from the rest of the world. I hated the quiver that started in my good leg and worked its way through my malformed body until I was shaking like a palsied thing, vibrating like a victim of electroshock. The pendulous masses on my chest and back and buttocks quivered like pulpy cockscombs. If my jaw had been anything near normal, my teeth would have been chattering. As it was, saliva flew from the open proboscis of my bone-thrust of a mouth and I drooled on myself even while I wept.

I went to my good knee in the cinders and then forced my other leg down. It would be very difficult to rise again without anything to grip, anyone to help me up.

At that instant I did not think that I would rise again.

The cinders cut through the thin cloth of my cloak and cotton trousers into the flesh of my knees.

This would be where Ozymandias Prather’s father would have brought the Piece. This is the heart of the heart of evil. Whatever was here would have welcomed him . . . accepted the Piece into its dark keeping.

I heard a rustling above and around me as if large wings were being opened. I looked up but there was only darkness, storm-cloud dark, raven-black. A great weight seemed to press me closer to the cinders.

I fell forward onto the rocks. I broke my fall with my good hand, but my bulbous forehead still scraped the cinders. Blood dripped onto the black stones.

He laid his head back on his pillow and went to sleep.

My breath rasped. My face was pushed downward as surely as if there were a taloned hand on my neck, forcing me into the sharp-edged cinders.

Something stirred under the stones.

The kids had told of basements and subbasements, catacombs where things moved deep out of the light. The corpse of Mrs. Duggan dragging its rotted remains up varnished stairs. Worse things moving behind it.

I heard stirring and shifting under the stones. There came a deep sliding and then an upward shift. The cinders moved under me like earth suddenly turned rubbery in an earthquake. I tried to grab the ground with both hands but the pulpy flipper that was my left hand slipped out of its cloak and flailed helplessly. The cinders slashed at the soft, gangrenous flesh there until blood splattered my cheek.

I allowed the weight of my horrible skull to pull me the rest of the way down, my brow pierced to the jutting bone by cinder edges now, my gasping mouth against the iron- flavored rock. The shifting continued until the entire center of the square was bowing upward like the water above a shark on its final run.

I felt the something directly under me then . . . knew that it would be mere seconds until the long white fingers thrust up through cinders to close on my throat . . . knew that the long teeth would be seconds behind that . . . could all but hear the walnut-cracking snap and crack of bone and cartilage as the jaws just inches below me now surfaced and closed on my face and skull . . . I could imagine the last glimpse from those multiple eyes, red beyond the knowledge of red, swallowing my soul in my last moment of knowing . . .

I gasped and sat up.

The great square of cinders bowed five feet above the level of the foundation stones and collapsed like a trampoline suddenly losing tension.

I could see beyond the stones. Leaves on the oaks across the street stirred in a sudden chill breeze. There was no other noise.

After several moments . . . after I was sure that whatever had almost come for me had nothing to do with the Piece, or Mr. Prather’s Device . . . I rose to my good knee, managed to leverage myself to my feet, wiped the streaming blood from my brow, and limped toward my greenhouse and tunnel and home.

One of my favorite bits of poetry comes from Shelley’s strange homage to John Keats, the pastoral elegy Adonais:

Life, like a dome of many-colored glass,
Stains the white radiance of Eternity,
Until Death tramples it to fragments.

As a child, after reading that, I used to lie awake in my bed in the tunnel, listening to Old Sook rattle and snore behind the curtain of burlap that separated our niches, and I would imagine that dome of many-colored glass . . . I would imagine coming up from the tunnel in daylight, not night, and emerging in the beautiful dome of many- colored glass, not the pale and shattered wreck of the greenhouse.

I can hear the trampling of my dome to fragments this final night before the circus lifts stakes and leaves, these final hours after the total midnight of my soul.

I think that I might kill Ozymandias Prather for the false promise he had made me. He had invited me not just to the Kingdom of the Blind, where my terrible ugliness might not be found, but beyond that . . . to the Ultimate Kingdom where my ugliness would simply cease to exist.

Where I would be normal.

Where the world would cease to be a robe of razor blades flaying me more surely than the cinders had, and become a warm blanket wrapped around a shivering child. Would become my mother’s arms.

Goddamn Ozymandias Prather to hell.

But even as I see myself killing the tall man with the dead face, I know that I will not touch him. I have never knowingly hurt any person.

Except the twin you murdered, I correct myself.

I groan and turn my face to the cold stones. This was not my fault, I tell myself. It was not really a twin. Not yet. Only cells.

Old Sook told me, the night after we returned from the specialist in Peoria She had been drinking the black cherry wine that she made up each autumn “You not the only one in your mama’s belly before you was born,” she said, not looking at me, her wrinkled face flickering from three dimensions to two in the candlelight “That professor doctor-man we called back when your mama went into the labor pains two months too early, he look through that little shiny scope of his and say that you have a baby brother, a twin baby like you. Only you swallow him up like a big fish swallow a little ’un. He say you gobble up this little ’unculus so’s you can live your own self. What we wonder now, my little darling baby, is was it worth it? Was it worth it?”

And she had started crying and had not stopped until she had started snoring I was sure the next day that she did not remember telling me. It was months before I found the word she had been trying for: homunculus.

Not the tiny human child I had imagined then, nor even the fully formed fetus I had nightmares about later, I know now, just a bundle of cells not much smaller than the bundle of cells that I was then.

But would we have been normal if we had both developed?

I scrape my bleeding forehead against the stone and try to think of other things. Once I had tried to speak to Father O’Rourke in the rectory garden about this thing, but I had begun weeping and slobbering instead. Father O’Rourke had hugged me to him, ignoring the stench and slobber.

Time to tell Prather that I failed.

For the last time, I push away my pillows, fling my blanket into a comer, and drag myself up stone stairs into the lighter darkness of night.

The WCTU women had their tent down by midnight, the American Legion half an hour later, and the JayCees by one a.m. By two-thirty the rides had been dismantled, the Freak Show canvas folded back in trailers, the midway disassembled, and the circus animals fed and sent to sleep in their traveling cages. Only the elephants continued to make noise, their trumpeting sounding like the cries of scalded women in the night.

By three-thirty a.m. the Peabody-Ozymandias Traveling Circus and Oddity Emporium was nothing more than a series of trucks and trailers on a filthy field. The roustabouts had quit shouting and grunting, even the elephants had quieted, and now the diesel engines began growling on the trucks. I scraped my way out of the line of trees and shuffled to Mr. Prather’s trailer. He opened the door immediately.

“Come in, Benjamin.”

I hesitated on the step. Most of my wounds had caked over, but some blood still found its way into my eyes. “I foiled,” I rasped.

Mr. Prather shook his head and pulled me into the darkness of his trailer. His touch was firm but gentle. “You haven’t failed,” he whispered. His voice seemed to be coming from his belly rather than his face.

“I failed,” I said again. “I could not find the Piece. The Device will not work.”

“Come here, Benjamin,” whispered Ozymandias Prather and pulled me deeper into the dark. I could hear others breathing in the room. There were large shapes—not normal shapes—on the couch at the end of the room. I realized that some of his freaks were here. I did not want to see them.

“Look,” he said and turned on the light table.

I glanced over my shoulder toward the couch, despite my wish not to see. The light did not reach that far, but I could make out a young man who looked like a snake, another man—thin, with skin as green as very new cheese or very old meat—and there, in the corner beyond the ancient X-ray machine, something larger and much more terrible . . .

“No, here,” said Mr. Prather and turned me back toward the light table.

My own X-ray photograph was there. I knew it was me . . . the twisted spine, the massive, misshapen upper arm, the fused ribs . . .

Mr. Prather’s strong finger stabbed down just above the white glow of my sternum in the X-ray image. “See?”

I saw. It was not very large really, no more than a few centimeters across. It looked almost, but not quite, round. There were teeth there, rather like the ratchet teeth on a small gear, but far more irregular. A thin, rodlike extension of the thing ran deeper, between the fusion of metal and rib cage, like a filament through my heart and into the spine.

“What does it do?” I whispered. I could not have understood the rattle of my own words.

“We don’t know what it does, what part it plays,” whispered Ozymandias, “but it is as necessary as any other part of the Device.”

I turned to look at him, aware of the stirrings on the couch, in the corner.

“We will need it, Benjamin,” he whispered. His mouth was inches away but there was no breath from it.

I turned to run but they had me before I got halfway to the door. I was weeping, but not at the terrible reality of my situation, only at the absurdity of the thought that I could successfully run away from someone.

Outside, all the diesels roared to life at once. The noise made me clap my hand and flipper over my ears. My beekeeper’s hat and veil rolled away under the X-ray machine.

“Take him to his cage,” said Mr. Prather. He had never turned away from the light table, as if the only thing about me that was worth his attention was there.

I tried to scream then, but whatever noise I made was lost in the roar of diesels as the first trucks began pulling out of the field onto First Avenue, one after the other.

As they hurried me out the door, Ozymandias Prather finally turned from the glowing board. “I promised you, didn’t I,” he said in that oddly booming, barely human voice, “that you could join the freak show?”

They found Joseph Merrick dead, in his bed, shortly after three p.m. on Friday, April 11, 1890. Although his body had continued to degenerate and become more terrible to behold in recent months, his spirit had been at peace for some time.

Joseph had realized his lifelong dream of visiting the theater. He had visited a country estate called Fawsley Park for six blissful weeks and had walked its fields, picked violets along its streams, and taken tea in its garden. Dr. Treves later wrote of receiving a gift of flowers from his friend in the country; they were the commonest of hedgerow plants, but Merrick had pressed, banded, and wrapped them as if they were the rarest and most lovely specimens ever gathered.

The wonder of the theater, and the country, and of his newfound friends never left Joseph Merrick. He was to say a few weeks before he died, “I am happy every hour of the day.”

After Merrick’s death, his friend Dr. Treves directed the taking of plaster casts of Joseph’s head and limbs, performed the autopsy and dissection, and supervised the mounting of Merrick’s bones onto a wire armature so that the skeleton could be displayed.

It is displayed until this day in a side hall of the Medical College of the London Hospital. Nearby, also on display, are the cap and burlap mask he wore, and a model church he had given a lady friend as a gift. Almost unnoticed in the rear of a secondary display case lies a small bunch of dried flowers wrapped in a ribbon from which all color has fled.

The Night seems gone because the lights of the midway gleam brightly whenever they open the fourth wall. Whenever I am exhibited.

I call for help, try to reason with those who have paid to see me, but the crowds shrink back from the stench and senseless noise. I think that they see my tears, but I cannot be sure.

I dream of the familiar streets of Elm Haven and the familiar faces at the windows of the houses there, feces watching me without fear, frequently smiling and waving as I pass. Sometimes I awaken to the sounds of the tires on pavement and the roar of the engines, and realize that I have lifted my good hand in a return wave.

The others do not speak freely when my cage is opened, but from the excitement behind their hushed voices, I sense that the journey is continuing. The Device is growing.

Perhaps they need only a few more Pieces.

Sometimes I convince myself that Father O’Rourke will track them down, find me, free me. If there is anyone in my life who I believe has confronted evil in all of its arrogance and terror, it is Father O’Rourke. Sometimes, when I have wept for hours and feel that the Night is nearing its end, I truly do believe that Father O’Rourke will find me and take me home.

At other times I know better.

There is a single high window on the for wall of my cage when the fourth wall is drawn shut, and by pinching my fingers in front of my eyes, I can make the midway lights through the glass gleam like a dome of many- colored glass. When I do that, I try to remember the penultimate stanza of Adonais.

That light whose smile kindles the Universe,
That Beauty in which all things work and move,
That Benediction which the eclipsing Curse
Of birth can quench not, that sustaining
Love Which through the web of being blindly wove
By man and beast and earth and air and sea,
Burns bright or dim, as each are mirrors of
The fire for which all thirst, now beams on me,
Consuming the last clouds of cold mortality.

Father O’Rourke once told me that all choices are ours to make. All futures are ours to choose.

Joseph Merrick had simply removed all pillows except for one. And then he had laid back his head to sleep. He was twenty-nine years old.

It is cold here tonight, but the blanket they give me is warm. My head is so much heavier these days that when I doze off sitting in my nest of pillows, my forehead touches my knees and the pain brings me awake in an instant. The cuts and scars across my brow have never healed properly. The temptation to kick the pillows aside, to lay one soft pillow down upon the cot they gave me, to lay back my head and close my eyes . . . the temptation is very strong.

But not quite yet. There may be pantomimes yet to be enjoyed, flowers to be gathered by streams I have not yet visited. Though the season grows toward its end, the leaves brittle, and the Night as cold as a dead mother’s breast, I think that there is time still to dream, and wait, and perhaps to hope.

All futures are ours to choose.

The show rolled on . . .